<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The articles of lete and courte for the lyberties of Southwarke</title>
            <author>Southwark (London, England)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1561</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 23 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12619</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22943</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101709</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837517</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837517</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1843</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12619)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1843)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1009:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The articles of lete and courte for the lyberties of Southwarke</title>
                  <author>Southwark (London, England)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Ihon Cawood, prynter to the Quenes Maiestie. Cum priuilegio Regiæ Maiestatis,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>. Anno. M.D.LXI. [1561]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Probably issued with with "The charge of the Court Baron" [of Southwark], 1561--STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures:  A-B⁴ C² .</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; trimmed at head, affecting running title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Courts baron and courts leet --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1843:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1843:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶ The Articles of <hi>Lete and Courte</hi> for the Lyberties of <hi>Southwarke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Imprinted at London by Ihon <hi>Cawood, Prynter to the Quenes Maieſtie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Cum Priuilegio Regiae Maieſtatis.</p>
            <p>Anno. M.D.LXI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:1843:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1843:2"/>
            <head>ARTICLES.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>YRST, you ſhal inquire and true preſentmente make, by the othes that ye haue taken of all youre Hedboroughes, with there decennaryes and other of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fycers, with al other perſons and reſyentes that oughte to be here at thys Courte and lawe daye, and yf any of them make default ye ſhall preſent theyr names.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhall inquire yf anye rightefull cuſtome or lawefull duetye, as hed Siluer, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon fyne, or ſmoke money, as commenlye (men call it) be withholden or withdrawen from the Lorde of thys Courte and lete, howe long it hath bene withholden, by whom, and in what bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyffes tyme it ſeaſed, and by whoſe procurement and in whoſe defaulte and preſente their names, that proces maye be made out of this courte to reſtore and recouer the ſame againe.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhall further inquire, what ye paye for your common fyne, or Sheriffes yelde, in carten, at thys daye, and whither it hath bene gathered amongeſt you as it hath bene vſed and accuſtomed before thys tyme, and be redye to be payde in Courte.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhall inquire for Gods part and behalfe of all Heretykes, and Lolleres, and of al theym that preache, teach, and kepe any erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and heretical opinions, contrary to the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike
<pb facs="tcp:1843:3"/>faith of Chryſt, and of the Quenes Maie ſties godly procedynges, and of their adherentes and ſcoles: Heretikes be they properly that hold any erronious opinions agaynſte the faythe of Chryſt and ordynaunces lefully vſed in the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che: And Lollers be they that eate fleſhe in times of abſtenence, and prohibited by the lawe of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye Churche, that be not Sicke or weke or haue any lycence for the ſame.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhall inquire of all traytours both by the common law, &amp; by the ſtatute law: A traytor by the common lawe, is properly, he that doth counterfeyte and make falſe money, or doth clyppe the Quenes coyne, waſſhers or demyny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhers of the ſame coine or any other lawful coine that is permitted and ſuffered to be curraunte within thys Realme, to the derogacion of the Quenes prorogatyue royall and indempnitye of her hyghnes Subiectes, Treaſon by the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute is where a manne dothe counterfeyte the Queenes Seales or anye of theym, Signe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuell, ſtampe or ſignet for anye faulſe intente or purpoſe: Pety Treaſon is wher the wyfe appren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tys or ſeruaunte dothe kyll her huſbande or the ſeruaunte or apprentyces hys mayſter or anye other perſonne that owe the dutye, obedyence, or confydence to them.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhall inqnyre of all manner of
<pb facs="tcp:1843:3"/>murders, whereof ſomme be more haynous then ſome, as wylfull murder, whyche is of a malyce pretenſed or lyinge in wayte to ſleye a man, and accordynge to that malycyous intente and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, ſleyeth hym ſoo that he whyche is ſlayne make no defence agaynſt hym, yf anye manne do ſley any by chaunce, that is mans ſlaughter whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is felonye: and therefore yf the quenes high nes graunte to anye man a generall pardon, for all maner of felonyes, excepte it be contayned within the ſame, thys worde murder, he ſhal dye for the ſayd murder, and of murders by myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune, murder in a mans owne defence.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhall inquyre of all maner of felonyes, Robberyes, and Burgularyes. Felo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny is yf a man take felonyouſly or wyth a feloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous intente, anye manner of goodes, or Cattels, of any other perſon aboue the vale we of twelue pence, as money, Apparell, Oxen, Horſſe, or Shepe, and ſuche other lyke thynges, for the whyche by the lawe of the Realme, he ſhal be ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kenne for a fellon, and ſuffer deathe, and forfeyt hys goodes, and Landes, Robberye is where a manne taketh wyth force from anye perſonne, eyther by nyghte or by daye, anye manner of thynge of anye valewe by the hyghe waye,
<pb facs="tcp:1843:4"/>way and putteth hym in feare of lyfe, or lyme for the whych he ſhal loſe the benefytte of his clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gye, and ſhal dye by the newe ſtatute, and forfeit as aforeſayde, burgulary, is where a man with force feloniouſlye doth breake anye mans houſe, wyndowe, or wall, and albeit he take nothyng, yet he ſhall dye, and loſe the benefite of his clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gye, for that the lawe gyueth no man coloure to breake any mans houſe, for his houſe is his caſtell and ſauegarde.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhall inquire of <hi>Rape,</hi> Rape is properlye where any man receaueth anye mans Wyfe, Wydowe, or Mayden, and hath carnallye to do with her agaynſt her wyll: Yet although afterwarde ſhe conſent to the Acte, he ſhalbe ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for au offend our in the ſame, and ſhalbe iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged a rauyſher and ſuffre for the ſame, for bycauſe it is at the N. ſute.</p>
            <p>Alſo, ye ſhal inquyre of al maner of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaryes, aſ well before that felonye as of acceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes after the felonye Acceſſary, before the felony is where anye perſonne procureth and cauſeth anye man to ſteale or robbe anye perſon althou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghe he whych procureth thys Acte, be not at the deede doynge, yet he ſhall dye for it, aſwell as he that doth the Acte in deede: Acceſſarye after the felony is where the acte is fyrſte commytted and done, and afterwarde receaueth or taketh the thynge, ſoo ſtolyn, or helpeth to conuey hym, this is acceſſarye after theyr felonye, for the whyche
<pb facs="tcp:1843:4"/>he ſhall dye as wel as the acceſſarye before the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lony: And of all them that be goers on meſſage of anye ſuche felons whych be of the nature lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe of Acceſſaryes.</p>
            <p>Alſo, ye ſhal inquire of <hi>Pety Larciny,</hi> that is to ſaye, of pety pykers, and ſtelers of thynges of ſmale valewe, as Hennes, Pygges, Geeſe, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, ſheffes of Corne in the Felde, Pynnes, and Poyntes, vnder the vale we of twelue pence, for the whych he ſhall not dye, but otherwyſe be po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſhed as by Whyppyng, and by Stockes, oro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwyſe as ſhall ſeme to the diſcretion of theim that ſhal haue the Quenes lawes in gouernau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and the examination thereof.</p>
            <p>Alſo, ye ſhal inquyre yf any man hath taken the pryuylege of the Church for murder, in hys owne defence or felonye, and hath abiured to the next Sentuary, accordynge to the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute laſte made for abiuration, and retourned oute of the ſame into thys Lordeſhyp, and hath not obtayned the Queenes pardon for the ſame.</p>
            <p>Alſo, yf anye man hath bene arreſted for ſuſpicions of Felony, murder, or robbery: And hath ben lette at libertie without ſuffycient bayle takenne by two Iuſtyces, one of the <hi>Quorum,</hi> and another of Peace, accordynge to the lawe in that behalfe, the whyche is an eſcape in the lawe, in hym that ſoo dothe lette hym goo wyth oute bayle.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1843:5"/>
            <p> Alſo ye ſhall inquire of all Cutpurſes, and pickepurſes that repayre to anye fayres, or markettes or other lefull congregations, of the quenes ſubiectes, there &amp; at that tyme, to picke ſteale and imbeſyl any maner of money, or Iuels contrary to the law, agaynſt them ordayned and prouyded.</p>
            <p>Alſo, ye ſhal inquyre yf any man haue abiured the realme, for anye maner of offence of murder, felony, or robbery, &amp; is retorned &amp; dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling here with out the Quenes pardon, whyche as a man with out the Queenes protexcion, and not meate to dwel among the Quenes ſubiects by the lawe.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhall inquire of al thoſe that cut out mens tounges, put out mens eyes, contrary to the Statute in that behalfe, made and prouy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhall inquire yf any man haue made anye reſcues vppon any of the Quenes offi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cers in ſeruynge anye proceſſe oute of thys court, or other wyſe doynge theyr duetye, or yf any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe be withholden that was lefullye ſtrayned for any of the Quenes dueties or otherwyſe.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhall inquire of al outecryes, and hues, made in the nyghte, to the diſturbaunce of the Quenes Subiectes, beynge in Gods peace, and hers, wherby that ſuch offenders may entre
<pb facs="tcp:1843:5"/>into theyr howſes, when they are abrode to do or commit any murder, felony or Robbery, or anye other like offences contrary to the lawe.</p>
            <p>Alſo, ye ſhal inquire of all aſſaultes, fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, batteryes, and bloudſhedes, done and commit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted againſt the Quenes peace, that is to ſai, that he that with force or other acte commeth to any man, he maketh the aſſault: And he that draweth the fyrſt weapon maketh the affray, and he that draweth the fyrſt bloud is giltye of the bludſhed.</p>
            <p>Alſo, ye ſhal inquyre of all pounde and cage berkers, which is an offence, and fynable by the lawe, that is to ſay, the pound brech. v. li. and the cage breking is finable as in caſes of reſcus.</p>
            <p>Alſo, you ſhal inquire of al theim that vſe anye vnlawefull games, as Dyce, Cardes, Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, Boulles, Claſhe, Tennis, and other ſuche lyke prohybyted by dyuers ſtatutes, and ſpecy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally by the laſt ſtatute of Anno. xxxiii. Henr. viii.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhal inquire yf any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen any Landes into Mortmayne, that is to ſay to any ſpirituall vſe or perpetuities as Guyides, Fraternities, or any other lyke vſe withoute the Quenes ſpecial lycence, hadde and obtayned for the ſame, the which la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des be forfeit by the law. &amp;c</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhall inquire of all treaſure troue within the precynte of thys lordeſhip, that
<pb facs="tcp:1843:6"/>is to ſay, yf any man haue found any Golde, &amp; ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, money, Plate, bullen or anye other Iewels, which is called properlye treaſure, hydden and belongeth to the lorde of euery Lordſhyp, where any ſuch is founde.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhall inquire yf any man vſe to kepe any market in the churche. or churchyarde, or anye other hallowed place whiche is prohy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byted by the lawe.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhall inquire of all home So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyns that is to ſay al ſuch that with faſing &amp; bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng, come to mens dores or houſes, &amp; their brag and threaten anye of the Quenes ſubiectes, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them in feare and dreade that they dare not come out of their dores, or ſit in their ſhoppes, to ply theyr handy craftes &amp; bodely labours.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhal inquire of al thoſe that be of thage of .xii. yeares or aboue, &amp; haue dwelt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this lordſhip, by the ſpace of a yeare and a day, and be not ſworne to be the quenes lyege people, and what perſon doth tetaine the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that they may be commaunded to bring them in to be ſworne.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhal inquire of al weyfes and ſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yes found and ſtrayed into thys Lordſhyp weyfes, is where anye man hath ſtolen anye thynge, and loſt it within thys Lordeſhoppe and is fiede and in whoſe hande it is: Strayes, is where any Cattell or beaſt commeth into thys lordeſhyppe
<pb facs="tcp:1843:6"/>eſtraunge, and no man knoweth who is the ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhal inquyre of al regrators and foreſtallers, are grator is he that biech al the ſtore of any thing in the markette to thintente to haue muche in hys owne handes, to make the pryce greate, Aforeſtaller is he that lyeth by the waye, and byeth any thyng before it come to the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kette, wherby there commeth oftentimes a great ſcarutie and neceſſitie.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhall inquire of al thoſe that vſe to ſhoote in anye Croſbowe, that maye not dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend one hundreth pound by the yeare, or ſhoote in any Handegonne contrary to the ſtatute, that haue not a ſuffycyent plakette or lycence, for thet ſauegarde in that behalfe, and that vſe to ſheote in them otherwyſe then is lymytted in the ſayde Statute.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhall inquyre of all theim that be vnder thage of three ſcoore yeare, and aboue the age of ſeuen yeares, whyther they vſe there long bowes, as by dyuers and ſondrye ſtatutes, it is commaunded and prouyded: And that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye mans ſonne, ſeruaunte, and prentyſes, haue a bowe and three arrowes at the leaſt: Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge as in the laſte Statute made the .xxxiii. yeare of kyng Henry the eight, it is mentioned.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhal inquire if aniſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger or alien
<pb facs="tcp:1843:7"/>to ſhute in any long bowe: for yf they doo, they be forfeyte: And it is laweful for any of the Quenes Subiectes to take them forfeyte.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhal inquire yf al Vacaboundes and valient Beggers, that come into thys lorde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyp to begge, hauing not the letters of lymitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thys hundreth.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhall inquire of the Conſtables within this Lordeſhyp, knoweth any Vacaboun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des, reſortyng or abydynge within this lordſhyp, and will not put them in Stockes, therto abyde by the ſpace of three dayes, and three nyghtes, gyuynge them no other ſuſtenaunce but breade and water yf that vacabounde be perſonable to bere ſuch dyate vpon payne of .xx. ſhyllnges for euerye defaulte.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhal in quire of al ſuch perſones as vſe to geue anye of the ſayde Vacaboundes, beynge in ſtockes, and maye bere the diate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſayde, anye other ſuſtenaunce then is afore reherſed for euerye perſon forfeyteth to the lorde twelue pence.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhal inquire of al eues droppers and nyght walkers, that vſe to ſtand at mennes doores, and wyndowes, to herke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and here tales, what is ſaid in a mans houſe, and cary tales from neyghbour to neyghbour, to ſette theym at vary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1843:7"/>
            <p> Alſo ye ſhal inquire of all common haſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerders, that is to ſay, of thoſe that be maſterles, and that no man can tel from whence they come and whither they wyll, and ſyt and play at dyce, cardes, and wache all nyght, and ſlepe all daye.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhall inquire of al petye Hoſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes, and blynde alehouſes, that is to ſaye, they that kepe any lodging in their houſes, and haue not a ſygne at theyr dore, or ſel ale, and be not auc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>toriſed by the Iuſtices and other officers.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhall inquire yf there be anye man that kepeth any Greyhounde, that may not diſpende xl. s. by the yeare, or yf there be any preſt that kepeth any Greyhounde that maye not dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pende ten pounde by the yeare.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhall inquire of all hunters, and Fawkeners, and takers of feſauntes, and partri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges within the precincte of this lordeſhyppe.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhal inquyre of al Fiſſhers, and Fowlers, within the precincte of thys Lordſhyp, and ſpecially of all them, that take Hernes, Cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, and other foules of warren,</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhall inquire yf anye man haue incrochid vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Quenes hygh wayes, or other wayes in diminyſhyng or imparyng the ſame, or any of them, for the inlarging of his own ground.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1843:8"/>
            <p> Alſo ye ſhal inquire of al Sewers, dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, mylbers, and gutters, be ſcoured and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged ſo that they be not noyfull to the Quenes ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſectes, or ſtoppe any water courſes.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhal inquire of al purpreſters, by water and by land, that is to ſay, of al them that do ley by water or by land any great tember log<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, ſtone or donghiles by the which the Quenes liege people are letted or greued of there com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon paſſage.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhal inquire if anye Brydge be broken, or yf anye houſe, hedge, or pale, be caſte downe and lie in the high way, wherby the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes liege people be letted of ther common paſſage to market, or to the churche or otherwyſe.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhal inquire of al bond brekers and fyllers vp of dyches, that is to ſaye, of theym that remoueth any marke or mere ſtones, that is ſette betwene the Quenes high waies, and other lordes grounde, abuttyng vpon the ſame.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhal inquire of all whight taw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers, that ſell not good chafer, as they oughte to do reſonable, and byeth their ſkyunes, in anye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places, then in townes, or markettes.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhal inquire of al Cordwainers, and Artyffecers, that make not good ware for the people as they ought to do.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1843:8"/>
            <p> Alſo ye ſhal inquire of al Bouchers, and Poulters, and other Vittellers, that is to ſay, yf any Boucher kyll and ſell any corrupte bytayle, &amp; ſel to exceſſyuely in price, that is to ſaye, aboue a peny gaynes in a ſhyllyng, for they ought to haue no more by the St<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tute: And the Poulter ſel any corrupte or ſtale pultrye and vnholeſome for mans bodye, and for to exceſſyue pryce.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhall inquyre yf the Fyſhers, and other Vittelers, do bring to markette and ſel good and holſeſome, &amp; ſeaſonable fyſhe for mans body, and lykewyſe ſell it not to exceſſyuelye.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhal inquire of all Bakers, that bake vnholeſome breade, and breake the aſſile, and make not iiii. loues for a peni two loues for a peny, and one for a peny, &amp; ſet not theyr markes vppon the ſayde breade that it maye be knowen, whoſe breade it was.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhal inquire of all Brewers, that brewe not good and holſe ſome Bere and Ale, of good and ſufficient ſtrengthe, accordinge to the price of malte, and whither they ſell anye oute of there dore before the ale taſter haue taſted it, and therof haue ſet pryce, and whether it put to ſale in veſſelles marked with the Antonye Croſſe or not.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhal inquire of all Huxſters, and Tapſters that ſell Beare, Ale, and breade, by any vnlaweful diſhes, booles, cuppes, &amp; meaſures vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſealed
<pb facs="tcp:1843:9"/>wherby the Quenes liege people are dyſceaued, not knowing what they haue.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhal inquire of al them that vſe to ſel by double or falſe waightes, and meaſures, that is to ſay, to by a great, and ſel by a leſſer, lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge the iuſt weyght, length, gage, and quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the ſtanderd.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhal inquire if al Brewers, haue theyr veſſells marked with the Anthony Croſſe, by the artiffycers of the compaſſe, and that the Bere barrell contayne .xxxvi. gallons, the Kyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derkyn .xviii. the Ale barrell .xxxii. the kylderkin xvi. and other veſſelles after that rate.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhal inquire of al Myllers, that vſe to take to exceſſiue tole, otherwiſe then they ought to do of right according to the old cuſtome and lawe.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhal inquire whither your cage, Stockes, or Cuckyng ſtole, be well and ſuffycy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently repared &amp; ſufficient for the punyſhment and ſaue kepyng, of offendors, &amp; whyther your But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes be well and ſufficientlye made for the mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce and increaſe of Artyllarye.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhal inquyre and preſent al the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that doth offende in the Statute of Apparell, made in the fyrſt and ſecond yeares of kyng Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyp and Quene Mary, that is to ſay, ſuche as do
<pb facs="tcp:1843:9"/>weare any Sylke, or veluet, in theyr hattes, cap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pes, ſworde gyrdells, dagers ſheathes, or ſpurre lethers, that be not worthe two hundreth poun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des in goodes, or may not ſpend twenty pounde by the yeare. &amp;c. And whither anye perſons kepe any ſeruaunt offendyng in the premiſſes, and do knowe thereof, and kepe him in his ſeruice by the ſpace of xiiii. dayes. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhal preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t al thoſe that take any fry or any kynd of Fyſhe, by any maner of vnlaw full ingine, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to the ſtat<gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> made in the firſt yeare of our ſoueraygne Lady he Quenes Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ieſtie that nowe is, for whych offence the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour ſhall loſe .xx. s. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhall preſente whether there be Surueyours by the hygh wayes, accordynge to the ſtatute, and whither all perſons, accordynge to the ſtatute, do labour .iiii. dayes in euery yere or not, and whyther your highwayes be in good ſtate and not in decay, vpon the paine limitted in the ſame ſtatute or not. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhall preſent that yf anye Bou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, Bruer, Baker Poulter, Cooke, or Fruterer ſhall at any tyme conſpire couenaunt, promiſe or make <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> othes, that they ſhall not ſell theyr vy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talles, but at certayne prices, or anye artifficer, workeman or labourer, do conſpire couenaunte or make any promiſe together, that they ſhal not make or do theyr workes, but at certayne prices
<pb facs="tcp:1843:10"/>and rates, or ſhal enterpryſe to fyniſhe that ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath begon or ſhal do but certayne worke in a daye or ſhall not worke, but at certayne tymes and howres, that then euerye ſuch offendour for the fyrſt offence, to loſe ten poundes, yf he be able to pay it, and yf not .xx. dayes impriſonment, and haue but breade and water, and for the ſecond of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, to loſe .xx. li. yf he be able, and yf not, then to be ſet on the pillary and loſe one of hys eares.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhall preſente whether that all ſuche as be inherytours of any eſtate of anye lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des or Tenementes, do kyll or cauſe to be kylled all Crowes, Chowes, Rowkes, that brede vpon the poſſeſſioners, accordyng to the Statute vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on payne of the penaltye conteyned in the ſame.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhal inquire of al them that law fully by any commiſſioners of muſters from the Quene ſhalbe commaunded to muſter and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully do abſent them ſelfes from the ſayd muſter, and haue noo lefull excuſe, the ſame perſon ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendyng ſhal ſuffre ten dayes impriſonme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out bayle &amp;c, except he do agre with the ſayd com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſſioners to paye xl. s. for the ſame offence to the Quenes Maieſtie vſe.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhall inquire of all Corway<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners whither they make good and laweful ſhoes and bowtes, and other like ware of lawefull and ſufficient leather, accordynge to the Statute or not.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1843:10"/>
            <p> Alſo ye ſhal inquyre yf all the officers within thys lordeſhyp, that is to ſay, the baylyfe concerning his office, the conſtable concernynge his office, the Ale conner concernynge his offyce the Scauengers, concerning his office haue wel and truely done the ſame, without any maner of extortion or other miſdemenure.</p>
            <p>Alſo ye ſhall inquire yf all defaultes, and playntes, that were preſented at the laſt law daye, be amended or not, as they ought to be. And of theſe poyntes and all other that ye were wonte to be charged with that is worthye to be preſented, ye ſhall go together and bryng in your verdycte.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
